Finding Aid for Sierra Club. Michigan Chapter records, 1964-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Legislation
  - "Polluter's Pay" (SB 375)
    - Lobby Report Forms, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Notes, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Press Clippings, 1990 (Box 16)
    - Sites of Environmental Contamination, 1989 (Box 16)
    - Copy of SB 375, 1989 (Box 16)
  - Quality of Life Bond Program, 1988-1989 (Box 16)
- Topical
  The Topical Files are organized into subseries by span dates. There is much overlap between subseries, so bulk dates have been provided to preserve a general chronology of the records. The two subseries are for records in the periods of 1966-1990 (largely 1980s) and 1983-2007 (largely 1988-2005).
  - 1966-1990
    The 1966-1990 subseries reflects major concerns of the Mackinac Chapter especially during the 1980s. For general discussions of issues and strategies, the researcher should see "Administration, Conservation Committee." Folders under the heading "Michigan Wilderness Act" include correspondence and news releases related to passage of the act as well as extensive files of newspaper clippings. The efforts of the chapter to monitor the management of federal and state lands in Michigan are documented in folders specific to the forests and parks. For example, correspondence regarding the Huron-Manistee Forest can be found in the folders of the same name. Researchers interested in the incineration of municipal waste and the Detroit incinerator should consult the 16 folders under the heading "Incinerator." Finally, a 1988 interview with David Hales (director of the Department of Natural Resources) conducted by chapter staff members may be found in the folder "Environmental issues, miscellaneous." Political endorsement activities from 1980-1985 are well documented in the "Political Endorsements, SCCOPE" folders. Some of the major issues during the late 1980s and early 1990s documented in this series include the opposition and eventual litigation involving the Detroit Incinerator, the resource management of the Huron-Manistee National Forest, and several legislative issues such as the use of off-road vehicles in state parks and requiring corporate polluters to pay for environmental clean-up.
    - Acid rain, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Administration of the Mackinac Chapter of Sierra Club
      - Chapter activity reports, 1983-1989 (Box 2)
      - Conservation Committees
        - Mackinac Chapter, 1980-1989 (Box 2)
        - Midwest Regional, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
      - General, 1983-1989 (Box 2)
      - Legal Defense Fund, 1979-1986 (Box 2)
      - Local groups within the Mackinac Chapter (Box 2)
      - Public Lands Committee, 1984-1987 (Box 2)
      - Regional councils (Box 2)
      - Treasurer's reports (scattered), 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Air Quality
      - General, 1981-1990; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Michigan Air Toxics Policy Committee, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Reports, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
    - Banquets, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    - Blanchard, Governor James J., 1983 (Box 2)
    - Bottle Bill (unclaimed deposit petition), 1989 (Box 2)
    - Council on Environmental Quality, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Coyotes, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Dow Chemical Company, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Earth Day, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Environmental alerts, 1974-1981 (Box 2)
    - Environmental bond issue, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Environmental education, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Environmental issues, miscellaneous
      - Correspondence, 1984-1990 (Box 2)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    - Environmental Protection Agency (budget problems), 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Forests and parks
      - Forest planning, 1989 (Box 2)
      - National forests and parks in Michigan, 1975-1990; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Fundraising, 1978-1989 (Box 2)
    - Funds Appeal, 1977-1989 (Box 2)
    - Gelman Sciences, 1988 (Box 2)
    - General Dynamics, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Grand Is, 1984-1989 (Box 2)
    - Grass Roots Effectiveness Project, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Great Lakes, 1982-1989 (Box 2)
    - Hiawatha National Forest, 1985-1989; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Highland Recreation Area, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Homestead Golf Course, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
    - Hooker Chemical, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Huron-Manistee National Forest, 1979-1989; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Incinerators (burning of municipal trash)
      - Correspondence, 1981-April, 1989; 6 folders (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, May, 1989-1990; 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 3)
      - Lawsuits, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
      - Studies, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - International Assembly of the Sierra Club (Ann Arbor), 1989 (Box 3)
    - Island Lake Recreation Area, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Land auctions (Muskegon County), 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - Land use policies
      - Correspondence, 1973-1980 (Box 3)
      - Legislation, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    - Mack, Senator Joseph, 1978-1984 (Box 3)
    - Mackinac, The (guidelines) (Box 3)
    - Medical wastes, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Environmental Council
      - General, 1984-1989; 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Minutes, 1983-1989; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Michigan Forestry Products Industry Development Council, 1985-1987 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Natural Areas Council, 1982-1989 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Natural Heritage Program, 1984-1987 (Box 4)
    - Michigan State Joint Committee on Administrative Rules (lawsuit), 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Michigan United Conservation Clubs (MUCC), 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Wilderness Act, 1987
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1980-1987 (Box 4)
      - "Michigan Wilderness Countdown Update", 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1985-1987; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Natural Resources Trust Fund, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Nordhouse Dunes, 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Nuclear disarmament (Box 4)
    - Nuclear power
      - Policies, 1973-1979 (Box 4)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
    - Nuclear wastes, (includes low level radioactive wastes)
      - Club policy, 1987 (Box 4)
      - General, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Off-road vehicle legislation, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Oil, gas, and mineral rights, 1981-1989 (Box 4)
    - Ottawa National Forest, 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Paper mills
      - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
    - Pesticide use, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Pictured Rocks National Lakeshore, 1969; 1977-1987 (Box 4)
    - Pigeon River State Forest, 1975-1984 (Box 4)
    - Political endorsements
      - Candidates' Forum (Central Michigan Group), 1982-1984 (Box 4)
      - Election campaigns
        - 1986 (Box 4)
        - (presidential), 1988 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - SCCOPE (Sierra Club Committee On Political Education), 1980-1985; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Population planning policies, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Polluters pay legislation, 1988-1990 (Box 4)
    - Presque Isle power plant, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Project ELF, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
    - Radon gas, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Recycling, 1988 (Box 4)
    - River protection, 1972-1989 (Box 4)
    - St. Mary's Peerless Cement Company, 1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Sand dunes, 1982-1989 (Box 5)
    - Sleeping Bear Dunes/Manitou Island
      - Correspondence, 1974-1986 (Box 5)
      - Legal, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Solicitation program, 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Solid waste
      - Landfills, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
      - Policies, 1984-1990 (Box 5)
    - Superconducting super collider, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - Superfund, 1980-1985 (Box 5)
    - Symbiosis, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - Toxic and hazardous substances
      - Correspondence and reports, 1981-1989 (Box 5)
      - Toxic Substance Control Commission, 1982-1989 (Box 5)
    - Trails
      - General, 1978-1985 (Box 5)
      - North Country National Scenic Trail, 1982-1988 (Box 5)
    - Urban Options (Sierra Club program), 1977-1984 (Box 5)
    - Users, 1978-1987 (Box 5)
    - Utilities regulation, 1977-1979 (Box 5)
    - Water Quality
      - General, 1976-1989 (Box 5)
      - Michigan Clean Water Campaign, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - Watt, James (recall petition), 1981-1982 (Box 5)
    - Wetland protection, 1978-1989 (Box 5)
    - Wilderness Programs
      - RARE II
        - General, 1978-1982; 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Questionnaires, surveys (samples), 1978 (Box 5)
      - Wilderness Activists, 1975-1986 (Box 5)
      - Wilderness Task Force, 1971-1981 (Box 5)
  - 1983-2007 (Bulk dates 1988-2005)
    The 1983-2007 (Bulk dates 1988-2005) subseries also covers a wide range of subjects, with many files relating to Ecosystem Biodiversity, Energy, protection of the Great Lakes, relationship with the Governor's Office, Litigation, and relationship with the Michigan Environmental Council (MEC).
    - Ecosystem Biodiversity
      - 1993-1994 (Box 17)
      - 1995-1997 (Box 17)
      - 2005-2006 (Box 17)
    - Energy
      - Great Lakes Council on Energy and Environment, 1988 (Box 17)
      - Public Utilities, 1984-1991 (Box 17)
      - Super Collider, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Governor's Office
      - Blanchard Administration/Environmental Policy, 1984-1988 (Box 17)
      - Boards and Commissions Workgroup
        - Reports of Findings, 1986-1987 (Box 17)
        - Clippings and Press Releases, 1986-1988 (Box 17)
        - Comments and Testimony, 1986-1988 (Box 17)
        - Notes, 1986-1988 (Box 17)
        - Correspondence, 1986-1991 (Box 17)
      - Engler Administration/Environmental Policy, 1991-1994 (Box 17)
      - Governor's Conference on the Environment, 1990 (Box 17)
    - Great Lakes
      - Great Lakes Advocates Information, 1988-1994 (Box 17)
      - Clippings, 1988-1989 (Box 17)
      - Great Lakes Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 17)
      - "Great Lakes Critical Programs Act" (S. 1646), 1989 (Box 17)
      - Eco-Region Program and Task Force, 1992-1994 (Box 17)
      - Ecosystem Stewardship Program, 1994 (Box 17)
      - Lake Superior Demonstration Zone, 1990-1991 (Box 17)
      - Great Lakes Protection Fund, 1988-1992 (Box 17)
      - Great Lakes Water Quality Agreement, 1990 (Box 17)
      - Zero Discharge Zone, 1991 (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 17)
    - Litigation
      - Crystal River, 1992 (Box 18)
      - Homestead, 1989-1992 (Box 18)
      - K & K Construction, 1997 (Box 18)
      - Takings, 1988-1995 (Box 18)
      - Wycamp Timber, 1991-1994 (Box 18)
    - Michigan Environmental Council
      (includes annual reports, correspondence, minutes, etc.)
      - 1990-1994 (Box 18)
      - 2002 (Box 18)
      - 2004 (Box 18)
      - 2005 (Box 18)
      - 2006 (Box 18)
      - 2007 (Box 18)
    - Newsletters, 1984-1999
      - Forest Network Newsletters (FAN), 1995-1999 (Box 19)
      - "Great Lakes Washington Report" (Sierra Club publication, scattered issues), 1988-1991 (Box 19)
      - Local groups in Mackinac Chapter (scattered), 1984-1994; 3 folders (Box 19)
      - "Sierra Club Great Lakes Bi-National Committee Newsletter" (scattered), 1988-1989 (Box 19)
    - Wildlife Management Project
      - Legislation, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - General Files, 1988-2000; 2 folders (Box 19)
        (includes correspondence, summaries, etc.)
    - Water Quality
      - Cogentrix Discharge Permit, 1990 (Box 19)
      - Groundwater Contamination, 1988-1989 (Box 19)
      - Injection Wells/Contamination, 1992 (Box 19)
      - Miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 19)
      - Risk Assessment, undated (Box 19)
      - Rule 57, 1983-1984 (Box 19)
      - Water Quality Standards, 1988-1993 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Agriculture, 1991 (Box 19)
      - Canoeing (Box 19)
      - Charles Stewart Mott Foundation, 1994; 2001 (Box 19)
      - Clippings, 1993-1994 (Box 19)
      - Coast Guard Live Fire Areas, 2006 (Box 19)
      - Council on Environmental Quality, 1988-1990 (Box 19)
      - Detroit Intermodal Freight Terminal (DIFT) Project, 2002 (Box 19)
      - Environmental Communication and Community Organizing (ECCO) Project, 2000-2005 (Box 19)
      - ECCO PMC, 2005-2006 (Box 19)
      - Environmental Enforcement Laws, 1982-1989 (Box 20)
      - Green Cruise, 2007 (Box 20)
      - Hunting and Fishing Conservation Partnerships, 2004 (Box 20)
      - International Assembly, 1988-1989; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Key States Gathering, 2005 (Box 20)
      - Lobby Day, 2004 (Box 20)
      - Political, 1988-2007; 2 folders (Box 20)
        (contains correspondence, fliers, calls to action, etc.)
      - Population Growth, 1989-1991 (Box 20)
      - Smart Growth Program, 2002 (Box 20)
      - State Programs, 1988-1992 (Box 20)
      - Tip of the Mitt Watershed Council, 2002 (Box 20)
      - Urban Sprawl, 1989-2003 (Box 20)
- Audio Visual Materials
  The Audio/Visual Materials series contains a slide show and several DVDs and CDs pertaining to the club's conservation and environmental protection endeavors. Currently, the small number of photographs have been left in their relevant folders (Boxes 13 and 16).
  - "Cougars Confirmed in Monroe County, Michigan,", January 12, 2005; DVD (Box 21)
  - "Isle Royale National Park,", July, 2005; CD of PDF files (Box 21)
    (Wilderness and Backcountry Management Plan for Isle Royale National Park and the associated Environmental Impact Statement)
  - "Living a Nightmare! Animal Factories in Michigan,", 2006; DVD (Box 21)
  - "Water is a Right", DVD (Box 21)
    (Documentary by Liz Miller about Highland Park's water issues)
  - "We Are the Sierra Club,", 1984; 120 Slides with cassette-tape soundtrack (Box 21)
Related Material
Finally, researchers interested in conservation issues should note that the Bentley Library holds the records of a number of other Michigan environmental groups including the East Michigan Environmental Action Council, the Ecology Center of Ann Arbor, Michigan Environmental Council, Michigan United Conservation Clubs, and the West Michigan Environmental Action Council.